BARB SNOBL

4033 Jordan's Grove Road Central City, IA 52214 319-438-6354(Home) 319-213-7980 (cell) snobl.barb@gmail.com

CAREER SUMMARY

A Registered Nurse with experience as a direct patient care provider in the medical and psychiatric nursing units of a hospital and as a case manager in the healthcare insurance industry. Most recently as a Chiropractor's Assistant, assisting in complementary care. Unique strengths include ability to work and establish rapport with diverse groups and individuals. Able to organize education, training and events at work and in the community. Works well with others in challenging situations to encourage and to ensure smooth work flow. Flexible to change and effective using multiple resources to further education, skills and knowledge.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

STIRLING BRIDGE PLACE Chiropractor's Assistant

2011-2012

Assisted the Chiropractor in managing and educating clients regarding the complementary services he provided. Provided internal and external customer service.

Cedar Rapids, Iowa

- Prepared clients for and completed scanning per office procedures.
- Completed general office duties such as preparing files, making copies, mailing client cards and letters, and general housekeeping duties.
- Greeted clients and placed in room for session. Completed notes for the Chiropractor during the session.
- Researched information for the Chiropractor and documented with noted references.
- Reviewed and revised office letters, policies and procedures as reviewed and approved by the Chiropractor.
- Assisted in making calls with outside vendors for needed equipment and troubleshooting when there were program concerns.
- Devised spreadsheets for improved documentation and monitoring client activity.
 Educated the office staff regarding utilization of the information.

PRINCIPAL FINANCIAL GROUP Hiawatha, Iowa Case Management Mentor 2008-2011

2001-2011

Mentored and supervised nine direct reports day to day operations, production and quality. Monitored and assessed individual and team trends and reported results to the case management team, leadership, and other departments. Assisted team manager in coaching, mentoring, providing training and technical expertise to case reviewers and non-clinical staff.

- Determined when in-depth technical research was needed during the case management utilization review process and made appropriate referrals to medical consultants and case management.
- Educated and promoted medical management strategies to customers and internal partners through meetings, presentations, and written correspondence to make sure everyone was seeing the big picture and on board.
- Answered questions and provided information about plan provisions and benefits applicable to proposed treatment in order to educate the members and the providers of what's available on the plan and how to best utilize.
- Initiated the disciplinary path for staff on team, when it was appropriate, engaging full support and follow through with Leadership and Human Resources to improve employee performance and results.

BARB SNOBL, Home: 319-438-6354, Cell: 319-213-7980, snobl.barb@gmail.com Page 2

Case Manager to Senior Case Manager 2003-2008

Responsible for applying data driven methods for members to fashion individualized case management care and worked with medical providers to help identify cost effective treatment alternatives. Advocated for the member to the full extent of existing health care coverage, conducted comprehensive clinical assessments, monitored member progress toward goal achievement and periodically reassessed changes in health status.

- Earned senior status as a Case Manager and also achieved Case Manager Certification.
- Encouraged communication, both internal and external, to enhance effectiveness of medical management services and member understanding. Received positive Customer Service Survey and internal feedback recognizing quality of work and communication.
- Applied Case Management concepts and problem-solving techniques to complex issues in order to promote optimum member outcome.
- Participated in a Pilot Program to test a new work flow process for the utilization and Case Management program designed to increase team effectiveness and improve communication.

Psychiatric Nurse Reviewer 2001-2003

Conducted daily telephonic psychiatric utilization review, adhering to criteria based decision tools, to evaluate appropriateness of admission and continued stay. Consulted with physicians, discharge planners, nurse case managers and medical directors, as needed, to deliver effective care, assist in discharge planning and when necessary identify the potential to use alternative care solutions. Maintained all required documentation in a timely manner.

- Utilized clinical knowledge and expertise in interpreting medical policy, medical criteria, and benefit information for members to meet the requirements for URAC (Utilization Review Accreditation Commission) and NCQA (National Committee for Quality Assurance) accreditation.
- Met both quality assurance and production metrics established by the utilization management team.
- Established and maintained positive relationships with treating physicians and other health care providers, through collaborative problem solving and discharge planning, which lead to potential cost savings for the member and the company.
- Received the Encore Award for my involvement working with a suicidal member and assisting the safety/security team to reach a safe and positive outcome.
- Asked by senior management to become a Case Manager when the position was available.

ST LUKE'S HOSPITAL

Cedar Rapids Iowa

1989-2001

Registered Nurse - Psychiatry

1992-2001

Worked direct care with children, adolescent, adult and geriatric patients in a hospital secure psychiatric setting. Addressed medication and diagnosis instruction with the patients and caregivers and facilitated parent skill building.

- Utilized behavior modification, individual treatment planning and educated clients and families regarding appropriate coping skills.
- Assigned as Charge Nurse.
- Awarded St Luke's Psychiatric Nurse of the year in 1994 and 1998. Held in highesteem by peers and leadership.

BARB SNOBL, Home: 319-438-6354, Cell: 319-213-7980, snobl.barb@gmail.com Page 3

Registered Nurse - Neurology

1990-1992

Worked in a medical critical care unit in the hospital setting. Administered medication, applied complex nursing skills, physical assessments and monitored, evaluated and documented patient progress.

Licensed Practical Nurse - Home Health Care 1989-1990

ADDITIONAL PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

The Abbe Center for Community Mental Health, residential setting. 1987-1990

Licensed Practical Nurse 1989-1990 Residential Worker 1987-1989

EDUCATION

Associate Degree in Nursing Certified in Case Management

Cedar Rapids, Iowa 1990

2006

TECHNOLOGY/COMPUTER SKILLS

Microsoft Office Suites; Outlook, Word, Excel Industry Software; Interqual, Careplanner, Milliman, Click4Care, Extra! Enterprise 2000(mainframe).

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

2011 Secretary for the North Linn Fish and Game Club; Member for two years.

Certified Hunter's Education Instructor, assisting in teaching Hunters Education classes and a coach for the YHEC (Youth Hunter Education Challenge) group, two years.

Past Medical Officer/Volunteer for the Central City Fire Department.

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

BAI (Basic Archery Instructor) 3 years and coach for Alburnett Archery team for two years.

4H volunteer for three years.